# Harshil Pisavadia

# MSc in Mechanical Engineering | Engineer In-Training

🗞 sites.google.com/view/Harshil-Pisavadia 🛮 in linkedin.com/in/Harshil-Pisavadia 🔃 researchgate.net/profile/Harshil-Pisavadia

@ pisavadi@ualberta.ca 🛘 +1 780 271 3845 💡 Edmonton, Alberta, Canada 🛽 Canadian and Australian Citizen

# 📑 TECHNICAL SKILLS

Finite Element Analysis (FEA) LS-DYNA, HyperWorks, ABAQUS, ANSYS

ANSYS, STAR-CCM+ Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD)

> MATLAB, Python, Bash, LATEX, SMath, Mathematica, Visual Basic, AutoHotKey Programming

3D Modelling SolidWorks, Blender, AutoCAD/Inventor, CATIA

# PROJECTS

#### DEVELOPMENT OF A DYNAMIC FAILURE MODEL FOR POLYMERIC ADHESIVES

APRIL 2020 - TODAY

Centre for Design of Advanced Materials One Slide Summary

Developing a cohesive zone finite element model to simulate the dynamic failure of adhesives used in hybrid armor systems for land vehicles under high-velocity ballistic impact using LS-DYNA simulation software package. This project is in collaboration with General Dynamics Land Systems, NP Aerospace, and Defence Research and Development Canada (DRDC).

LS-DYNA HyperWorks Blender SolidWorks Python MATLAB Bash

#### HEAVY-DUTY COMPRESSED NATURAL GAS FUEL RAIL DESIGN

May 2019 - August 2019



Led a team of five students to pioneer the design of a compressed natural gas fuel rail for heavy-duty diesel engines to be installed in a full-scale dual-fuel semi-trailer truck.

- > Complied with ASME/BPVC, NGV 3.1, and ISO 15500 standards to define design parameters
- > Performed detailed stress and deformation analysis of the fuel rail using ANSYS to locate high stress concentrations zones
- > Conducted CFD analysis inside fuel rail to determine the flow and temperature distribution using the ANSYS CFX module
- > Prepared reports containing cost estimates, 3D renders and detailed drawings of the prototype, and safety requirements

SolidWorks ANSYS SMath

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Today April 2020

Center for Design of Advanced Materials - Dr. James Hogan's Research Group, Edmonton, AB

Modelling Team Lead

- > Leading the CDAM modelling team to develop a state-of-the-art system-scale hybrid armor model
- > Simulating high-speed ballistic impact events on a full-scale hybrid armor model using LS-DYNA with parallel and cluster computing (bash scripting in Compute Canada)
- > Automating the 3D model generation of ceramic tiles taking into account manufacturing defects (e.g., tolerances and adhesive seepage) using Blender coupled with Python scripting
- > Communicating research output to industrial collaborators and academics through presentations in monthly Alliance Science meetings and biweekly group meetings
- > Leading biweekly writing workshops by mentoring graduate students to improve their article and thesis writing skills
- > Assisting the Principal Investigator in project and research management, including proposal drafting, budgeting, and scheduling

### December 2019 April 2019

Research and Development Engineer Intern

Collaborated with Milburn Mountain Defense and DRDC to design armor plates and platens:

- > Used SolidWorks and CATIA to create 3D models and drawings of armor plate assemblies
- > Communicated with collaborators through presentations and detailed technical reports highlighting updates to the design and methods used (e.g., coordinate-measuring machine, 3D scanner)

Collaborated with US Army Research Laboratory and DRDC for Synthetic Microstructure Project:

- > Performed MATLAB processing of material microstructures for next generation material development
- > Generated 3D representations of secondary phase particles using statistical distributions by assigning orientation angles, distances, and methods to populate them using MATLAB

#### December 2019 September 2019

#### Alberta Health Services, Edmonton, AB

Engineer Intern

- > Involved in the development of an osseointegration prosthetic limb protoype using reverse engineering techniques by 3D scanning, instrumentation techniques, and 3D modelling with SolidWorks
- > Performed dynamic analysis of a bone anchored hearing aid implant model using ABAQUS

#### January 2019 September 2018

#### International Cooling Tower (ICT), Edmonton, AB

Engineer Intern

- > Created cost estimate templates using VBA within Excel for sections of a crossflow cooling tower (e.g., fan deck, louvers, sealants, stairways) taking user inputs of overall dimensions and materials
- > Designed and developed detailed drawings of a sample testing rig using AutoCAD to analyse nozzle spray patterns and ensured strict company safety protocol under its operation
- > Modified and updated ICT design standards using AutoCAD, ensuring design constraints are satisfied
- > Reviewed, identified, and eliminated discrepancies in engineering drawings of a multi-million-dollar cooling tower project using AutoCAD

#### May 2018 August 2018

#### Dr. Morris Flynn's Research Group, Edmonton, AB

Research Assistant Participated in "Minimizing the Visible Plume Produced by Cooling Towers" research project in collaboration with ICT":

- > Developed conceptual designs of a counterflow cooling tower's plenum chamber using SolidWorks
- > Converted a coaxial plume MATLAB model to Python programming language

# December 2017 May 2016

#### Dr. Arthur Mar's Research Group, Edmonton, AB

Research Assistant

- > Developed a AutoHotKey script to efficiently export >300,000 crystallographic information files from Pearson's Crystal Database saving several months of processing time and funds to hire personnel
- > Presented research output of "Frustrated Machine Learning: The Case of Polymorphism in Titanium Iron Phosphide" at North American Solid-State Chemistry Conference 2017



#### EDUCATION

August 2022 September 2020

#### Master of Science in Mechanical Engineering

University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada

- > Cumulative GPA: 4.0/4.0
- > Thesis title: Development of a Dynamic Failure Model for Polymeric Adhesives used in Hybrid Armor Systems for Land Vehicles

Cohesive Zone Modelling | Impact Dynamics | Finite Element Analysis | Fracture Mechanics | Statistical Mechanics

#### April 2020 September 2015

#### Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering Co-Op, Mathematics Minor

University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada

- > Cumulative GPA: 3.8/4.0
- > Graduated with Distinction
- > Capston project: Heavy-Duty Compressed Natural Gas Fuel Rail Design

Computational Fluid Mechanics | Structural Design | Thermodynamics



## Publications

- > Pisavadia H, Toussaint G, Dolez P, Hogan J. Cohesive Zone Failure Modelling of Polymeric Adhesives used in Armor Systems. International Journal of Impact Engineering. (Submitted October 2021).
- > Mohamed M, Pisavadia H, Westover L. Dynamic Analysis of the Bone Anchored Hearing Aid System using Finite Element Method. Journal of Biomechanics. 124(2). (2020).
- > Oliynyk A, Adutwum L, Rudyk B, Pisavadia H, Lotfi S, Hlukhyy V, Harynuk J, Mar A, Brgoch J. Disentangling Structural Confusion through Machine Learning: Structure Prediction and Polymorphism of Equiatomic Ternary Phases ABC. Journal of the American Chemical Society. 139(49): 17870-17881. (2017).



#### **L** Additional Information

- > Proficient in English and Gujarati
- > Member of the Nautical Research Guild
- > Interests: Model ship building; Gardening; Health and Fitness; Cooking